

PROFILE

He is a registered mechanical engineer who had professional experiences in elevator installation and HVAC-R (heating, ventilating, Air -conditioning, refrigerating) installations commissioning before engaged in a teaching profession. He teaches mechanical engineering subjects for 8 years with research papers presented in an international, national and local Conferences. He also published his research work in a Scopus-Indexed conference proceedings.

CONTACT

09454186124

EMAIL:

xtian_mortelrme@rsu.edu.ph.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Design and Development of Machines Optimization of Machines Computational Fluid Dynamics Simulations

CHRISTIAN MALACAPO MORTEL

Assistant Professor III Romblon State University

ELIGIBILITY

84.35% Ratina

- Registered Mechanical Engineer
- National Certificate II in Refrigeration and Air-conditioning
- National Certificate II in Driving

EDUCATION

Master of Engineering (Mechanical Engineering)

Technological Institute of the Philippines Cubao, Quezon City CHED Scholar June 2016 – March 2018

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

Romblon State University
Odiongan, Romblon
With Academic Distinction, Leadership and Journalism Awards
June 2008 – March 2013

Romblon National High School

Romblon, Romblon June 2004 – March 2008

Bagacay Elementary School

Romblon, Romblon 2004

WORK EXPERIENCE

Romblon State University

Assistant Professor III – Permanent November 2022 – Present Designations:

Chairperson, BSME Program (August 2021-Present) Major Accomplishments:

- Submitted the necessary documents for application for Certificate of Program Compliance (COPC);
- Lead the program in the preparation and submission of the documents for the AACCUP Level 4 Accreditation; and
- Strategize interventions to increase the performance rate in the Board Examination.

Team Leader, Inventory of the Buildings, Electrical and mechanical Equipment

Land Use Development and Infrastructure Plan (LUDIP) Major Accomplishments:

- Submitted the Phase 1 of the project which is the Inventory of the all Buildings, electrical and Mechanical equipment of the Main Campus and satellite campuses; and
- Acquired equipment to be used in the building integrity assessment and mechanical and electrical evaluation.

Rombion State University

Instructor 1 – Permanent January 07, 2015 – November 2022

Designation:

Head, Mechanical Section Unit Physical Plant and Facilities Office (August 2020 August 2021) Major Accomplishments:

- Designed and cost estimated the sprinkler system and airconditioning system of the Construction of University Library; and
- Designed cost estimated the sprinkler system and airconditioning system of the Biology Laboratory of the University.

Rombion State University

Lecturer November 2014 – January 2015 Designation: Research Coordinator, CET

TrendWorks Aircon Inc. - Cadet Mechanical Engineer

June 2014-November 2014

Accomplishments:

- Supervised the installation of the Airconditioning systems of The Medical City, Pasig City.
- Supervised the installation of the replacement of Valves at the NAIA.

International Elevator and Equipment, Inc. - Project Engineer

January 2014- June 2014

Accomplishments:

- Supervise the installation of elevators at the different sites at the same time, prepare and collect the billing of all the assigned projects, namely:
 - AVIDA Towers, BGC, Taguig City.
 - W fifth Tower, BGC, Taguig City
 - Del Rosario Law Firm Building, McKinley

RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

Optimization of Straight-Bladed Darrieus Type Vertical Axis Wind Turbine for Low Wind velocity

https://doi.org/10.1051/e3sconf/202021102008

E3S Web of Conference (Scopus)

Publisher: EDP Sciences

Numerical Simulation of Two Dimensional (2D) Elliptical Shape Savonius Wind Turbine (SWT) Blade using Response Surface Methodology

Co-author of Engr. Charmaine F. Fetalver American Institute of Physics (IAP) Conference Proceedings 2534, 020002 (2022) (Scopus) https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0105197

Completed and On-Going researches and extension ENGAGEMENTS

RESEARCH

Completed

- Development, Performance Evaluation and Utilization of Tiger Grass Post Harvest Technologies Externally funded by DOST-MIMAROPA Local GIA
- Optimization of Straight-bladed Darrieus Type Vertical Axis Wind Blade for Low Wind Speed
- Value Optimization Among Process Parameters of Mungbean Shelling Machine
- Design and Development of Jackfruit Peeling and Slicing Machine
- Design, development and performance evaluation of Mungbean Shelling Machine

On-Going

Project Leader

 BASE Project: Building Audit and Energy Assessment; Basis for Policy and Program Development for Infrastructure Planning

Internally Funded Research

Project Member

 Harmonized and Unified Geographic Information System (HUGIS) Research Project

Project Member

 Establishment of Laboratory Scale Research Facility for Characterization of Ground Calcium Carbonates (GCCs) from Romblon Marble Wastes for Possible Commercialization and Industrial Use

Externally Funded Research by DOST-MIMAROPA Local GIA

EXTENSION

Completed

- Information Dissmination and Demonstration of Briquetting and Sieving Machine Facilitator
- Training Workshop on Prepaparing Project Proposals for Barangay Officials Facilitator

On-Going

Lead Proponent

 Technnology Transfer and Maintenance Operation Procedures of the Devloped Portable Tiger Grass Pollen Remover Machine

RESEARCH PRESENTATIONS

3rd National Conference on Food, Environment, Engineering and Technology

Bataan Peninsula State University

September 16-17, 2021

Computational Fluid Dyanamics of H-Darrieus Wind Turbine Blade using Response Surface Methodology

1st JESSD Symposium, International Symposium of Earth, Energy, Environmental Science, and Sustanable Development

Universitas Indonesia

September 28-30, 2020

International Integrated Research Conference

Ateneo De Manila University, Manila, Philippines

September 20 - 22, 2019

Optimization of Straight-Bladed Darrieus Type Vertical Axis Wind Turbine for Low Wind velocity

1st Annual National Philippine Consortium for Science, Mathematics and Technology (PCSMT)

La Trinidad, Benguet, Philippines

August 28 – 30, 2019

Design and Fabrication of Jackfruit Peeling and Slicing Machine

1st Research, Education, Business, Science and Arts International Conference (REBSAIC 2019)

June 22 - 24, 2019

Davao City, Philippines

Value Optimization among Process Parameters of Mungbean Shelling Machine through Response Surface Methodology

6th Pacific-Asia Conference on Mechanical Engineering (PACME)

August 29-31, 2017

Malate, Manila, Philippines

Design and Development of Mungbean Shelling Machine

All Researches above were presented in the Local In-research Presentations organized by the Research Unit of the University

PROFESSIONAL ORGANIZATIONS

Philippine Welding Society Philippine Society of Mechanical Engineers (PSME) Philippine Society of Mechanical Engineers (PSME)-Romblon Chapter ASIAN Intellect, Inc.

Member Member **Auditor** Member

SEMINARS AND TRAININGS

MIMAROPA Regional Stategic Planning and Futures Thinking **Agenda Setting**

Futures Thinking MIMAROPA April 19-21, 2023 Club Balai Isabel, Talisay, Batangas

Regional Consurtium Workshop: High Level Anticipatory Leadership and Governance Executive Course

Philippine Futures Thinking Society December 12-16, 2022

Capacity Building on Geographic Information System, Data Analysis, and Scientif Writing Workshop

April 25-27,1 2022 MAPUA Universiy

68th PSME Virtual National Conference

Philippines Society of Mechanical Engineers October 17-24, 2021

Special Course on Urban and Regional Planning

University of the Philippines September 6-17, 2021

3rd National Conference on Food, Environment, Engineering and **Technology**

Bataan Peninsula State University September 16-17, 2021

Training Workshop for Computer Aided Design System using SolidWorks and AutoCad Software

Nueva Ecija University of Science and Technology March 23-24, 2021

International Collaboration in Engineering, Science, and Technology for a Resilient New Normal

Polytechnic University of the Philippines February 22-28, 2021

Working Together, Moving Further: The RSU ISO 9001 Certification **Journey**

Romblon State University October 23, 2020

68th PSME Virtual National Conference

Philippines Society of Mechanical Engineers October 17-24, 2020

1st JESSD Symposium, International Symposium of Earth, Energy, **Environmental Science, and Sustanable Development**

Universitas Indonesia September 28-30, 2020

International Integrated Research Conference

Ateneo De Manila Philippine Continuing Profesional Development Training Center,

September 20-22, 2019

Hydrostatic Bench Training

HYTECH POWER INC. September 13-14, 2019

1st Annual National Philippine Council of Science, Mathematics and Technology (PCSMT) Research Congress

Philippine Consortuim for Science. Mathematics and Technology August 28-30, 2019

1st Research, Education, Business, Science and Arts Internation Conference (REBSAIC 2019)

Asian Intellect Organization June 22-24, 2019

Training Workshop for Patent/Utility Model Application WritingDOST

September 24-26, 2018

6th Pacific-Asia Conference on Mechanical Engineering (PACME) and 6th International Conference on Civil Engineering (ICCE) 2017 Nihon University and Technological Institute of the Philippines August 29-31, 2017

AWARDS RECEIVED

PAG-ASA ng RSU 2022

 LUWAY TEAM on the Development, Performance Evaluation and Utilization of Tiger Grass Post Harvest Technologies
 Romblon State University

Service Award 2022

 For serving as Chairperson of the BSME program from 2021 to Present College of Engineering and Technology

2020 Professional Growth Award

• Completion of Master of Engineering Program at the Technological Institute of the Philippines, Quezon City.

2nd Best paper

 2018 In-house review of Researches and Extensions Outputs Romblon State University
 Design and Fabrication of Jackfruit Peeling and Slicing Machine

1st Best Paper

 2017 In-house review of Researches and Extensions Outputs Romblon State University
 Value Optimization among Process Parameters of Mungbean Shelling Machine

2nd Best Paper

 2016 In-house review of Researches and Extensions Outputs Romblon State University
 Design and Fabrication of Mungbean Shelling Machine

BASIC INFORMATION

Residential Address:

Birthday:
Place of Birth:
Religion:
Civil Status:
Spouse:
Mother's Nam

Mother's Name: Father's Name:

Batiano, Odiongan, Romblon March 01, 1992

Romblon, Romblon Roman Catholic

Married
Abigail Merida Mortel

Myrna Malacapo Mortel Nemesio Meran Mortel

I hereby declare that the above particulars of facts and information stated are true, correct and complete to the best of my knowledge.

ENGR. CHRISTIAN M. MORTEL
Registered Mechanical Engineer